A Guide to the Williams Family Papers, 1819-1993
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Williams Family Papers 1819-1993 1850-1945
Thomas Balch Library
M 010
The Williams Family Papers includes materials from five families: Pearce, Wilson, Harrison, Williams, and Winslow. The papers comprise approximately six cubic feet, with five oversized boxes housing documents and artifacts. Inclusive dates are 1819-1993, with the bulk of the material dating from 1850-1945. The collection is arranged in series by family name, with the papers of individual family members as subseries.
Harrison Williams III and Constance deBordenave
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Harrison Williams III, Fairfax Station, VA and Constance deBordenave, Heathsville, VA.
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2003.0023, 2005.0109, 2005.0183, 2011.0160
Biographical Information
The Williams Family Papers contain materials from five families: Pearce, Wilson, Harrison, Williams, and Winslow. The families are related through marriage. Individuals appearing in the scope and content note as subseries are highlighted in boldface to aid researchers.
Pearce Family (Series I)
George Pearce (1792-7 August 1822) was born in Dinwiddie County, Virginia. There is little information available about his early life. He joined the US Navy on 20 June 1806 as midshipman, leaving from Petersburg, Virginia. He was commissioned a lieutenant on 24 July 1813, during the War of 1812. Pearce joined Lieutenant Thomas MacDonough on 14 August 1813 in the northern lakes theater at Lake Champlain, and took command of one of the sloops. Pearce and his sailors later assisted Lieutenant Colonel George Mitchell at a battle in Oswego Falls, New York in May of 1814. In a letter to his commander Mitchell commented on the bravery and tenacity shown by Pearce and his men.
Pearce married Eliza Lacey Stephens (ca. 1798-20 May 1860) in Erie, Pennsylvania 11 November 1819. She was also a native of Dinwiddie; little information is available about her early life. They had one child, Mary Wilson Pearce, born in Petersburg, Virginia on 8 July 1820. Pearce continued his service in the Navy, and the couple spent much of their marriage apart while he was at sea. George Pearce contracted yellow fever while aboard the Macedonian at Craney Island in the West Indies. Although it first appeared he would recover fully, he died of the disease on 7 August 1822.
After her husband's death, Eliza depended on Navy Pension Fund monies for which she was eligible as his widow. The pension fund was established by Congress in 1800 as an autonomous source of money for disabled naval veterans. In 1813 benefits were extended to widows and orphans of naval personnel who died in service, which expanded to include those who died or were disabled from service-related injury or disease. Administration of the fund was complicated by Congress deciding eligibility for awards and the amount each received. Pensions were awarded for five year periods, and could be renewed. Eliza's brother, W.J.N. Stephens (n.d.), who lived in Hardy County, Virginia (now West Virginia) and later her son-in-law, James C. Harrison (14 December 1819-21 November 1882), corresponded over the years with members of Congress and the Navy Department to help obtain her widow's pension payments.
Eliza resided in several locations during their marriage and after Pearce's death. Correspondence was directed to her in Erie, Pennsylvania, Brooklyn, New York, and New London, Connecticut where she resided for a time with her brother Clement Stephens (n.d.). By 1823 she had returned to Erie, where she remained until the end of her life; she appears to have lived with her daughter and son-in-law in Buffalo, New York for a period time around 1850. Eliza Pearce died 20 May 1860.
Wilson Family (Series II)
Little information is available about the Wilson family. Mary Wilson (n.d.) and her daughter Jane (n.d.) corresponded with Eliza Pearce, and appear to be related to her.
Harrison Family (Series III)
Jonas Harrison, son of William (n.d.) and Elizabeth (n.d.) Harrison, was born in Woodbridge Township, New Jersey, on 11 October 1777. There is little information available about the first 30 years of his life. He was admitted to the bar in Michigan Territory in 1807. By 1809 he lived in Lewiston, New York where he opened a law office and taught school. Harrison also served as Collector of Customs and Collector of Internal Revenue for the Niagara District, and Master of Chancery for New York. He married Betsey Cooke, one of his students, in 1811. Betsey Cooke Harrison was born 30 June 1795 in Wallingford, Connecticut to Lemuel (17 March 1762-?) and Betsey (?-1821) Cooke, who moved to Lewiston when she was two years old. Her brother Bates Cooke (1787-1841) read law with Harrison.
The Harrisons fled Lewiston along with the rest of the inhabitants when British and Native American allies burned the village in December of 1813, during the War of 1812. They took refuge in Batavia with other residents. Harrison and two other men wrote about the attack on Lewiston and observed that Fort Niagara appeared to be under fire in a letter published in the Ontario Messenger on 18 December 1813.
In 1815 the Harrisons settled in Buffalo Creek (present day Buffalo), New York residing there with their three children, Jonas (?-26 March 1836), Rachel (ca. 1818-?), and James Cooke Harrison (14 December 1819-21 November 1882). Harrison was an influential and, at least outwardly, wealthy man. He built a mansion often described as one of the finest in the city. He practiced law, was a founder of St. Paul's Episcopal Church, and served as a director for the Bank of Niagara. He was one of the original trustees when the village was incorporated in 1816, and served again in 1817. However, the country had fallen into financial crisis in the wake of the war, and Harrison's personal financial situation became increasingly dire. In 1814, he was nominated as a candidate for senator representing Niagara but declined, citing his deteriorating financial affairs which required all of his attention. Harrison was ruined in the panic of 1819, the first major financial crisis in United States history. The sale of his house was not enough to settle his debts, and his remaining property was sold by the New York attorney general. He left Buffalo for Detroit, Michigan in 1819, ostensibly on a prospecting trip. Notice of his arrival there was the last his family in Buffalo heard of him.
Harrison reappeared in Georgia in 1820 where he met Ellender Shannon (ca. 1803-28 August 1877), daughter of Owen (ca. 1762-1839) and Margaret Montgomery (1773-1854) Shannon. Shannon served in the American Revolution and received a bounty grant of land in Franklin County, Georgia. They had six children, most of whom later settled in Texas. The Shannons moved to Texas in 1821 as part of the Old Three Hundred, the first organized group of Anglo-American immigrants who settled in the colony established by Stephen F. Austin (1793-1836).
Harrison married Ellender on 26 June 1820; they moved to Texas in December of that year and settled in Shelby County. Jonas and Ellender Harrison had 8 children: Margaret, Jonas (ca. 1823-?), Jacob (ca. 1826-1867), John (ca. 1830-?), DeWitt Clinton (5 December 1827-6 March 1902), Thomas Jefferson (ca. 1834-1868), William Henry (27 September 1833-?), and Almira (ca. 1836-?).
In the beginning, Harrison presented himself as a frontiersman, taking no part in political or legal affairs and cultivating a rough and illiterate persona. He emerged from seclusion sometime prior to 1827, unexpectedly appearing in court on behalf of a man accused of a capital crime. His appearance and eloquent handling of the case surprised onlookers, and the story soon became legend. Author Edward Eggleston (1837-1902) created a rough-hewn character called Jonas Harrison in his book, The End of the World, A Love Story, based on tales about Harrison.
By 1827 Harrison had established a law practice and was taking part in community activities. One of his most famous clients was Sam Houston (1793-1863); he represented Houston in his divorce from Eliza Allen (ca. 1810-3 Mar 1861). Harrison was made Alcalde (municipal magistrate) of the district of Tenehaw in 1828, a position he held for at least three years.
As tensions grew between Texas Anglo-American settlers and the Mexican government in the late 1820's, Harrison initially supported the Mexican government. However, by the early 1830s he was corresponding with Stephen F. Austin, who led the revolutionary movement. He served as a delegate to the 1832 Convention, where the colonists lobbied the Mexican government for a number of changes and reforms. He also helped draft the San Augustine Resolutions advocating Texas' independence from Mexico. In 1835 he adopted the title "major" and actively recruited for the armies of Texas in spite of failing health. He died 6 August 1836. Harrison County, established in 1839, was named in his honor. Ellender did not re-marry. Their children and descendents settled throughout Texas. Ellender Harrison died 28 August 1877 near Arlington, Texas.
Betsey Cooke Harrison and her children returned to Lewiston in 1820 after being abandoned by Jonas. She was left with nothing, and her brothers helped provide for Betsey and her family until the children grew up. Bates Cooke took in James and raised him with his son, Joshua (1821-1908), sending James to the same schools. Jonas Harrison II moved to Erie, Pennsylvania where he worked in a store he co-owned, Tracy & Harrison. He died unmarried on 26 March 1836. Rachel married Moses Hall Fitts (1 January 1808-?), a teacher and member of the New York State Board of Education, with whom she had eight children. They later moved to California. Betsey Cooke Harrison died in Gouverneur, St. Lawrence County, New York 25 June 1872.
At the age of 14, James Cooke Harrison moved to Erie where he worked at his brother's store as a clerk. After Jonas' death in 1836, Harrison went to work at a store owned by Aaron Kellogg. In 1838 he joined Charles Manning Reed (1803-1871) in Reed's Erie steamboat business. Reed built and ran passenger steamships, and his operation was one of the biggest on the Great Lakes. Prior to the development of the railroad, emigration and trade to the west depended on steamers, and ship traffic on the lakes was substantial. Harrison started working for Reed as a clerk on the ship Erie. The Erie burned in July 1841, a year after he gave up the clerkship. It was one of the worst Great Lakes shipping disasters; over 200 people died, many of them Swiss and German immigrants. Harrison assisted with the recovery and burial of victims of the fire.
Harrison relocated to Buffalo in 1840, where he opened an office and managed Reed's Buffalo port interests. By the early 1840's grain shipments from the west had vastly increased, and the need for more grain elevators at the port to store and move the shipments became acute. Harrison and Reed built Reed Elevator in 1847, which they operated in conjunction with their transportation business. It burned and was rebuilt in 1859, and again in 1874. As the number of grain elevators proliferated owners became concerned about continuing to be profitable; Western Elevating Company was formed in 1859 to direct the industry. Harrison served as president of the organization in the early 1860's.
In addition to his work in the shipping industry, Harrison pursued other business interests in Buffalo. He was one of the first trustees of Erie County Savings Bank when it incorporated in 1854. It grew from a small operation, with around $600,000 in deposits, to over $11 million in deposits by 1883. Harrison was made vice-president in 1876, and succeeded the bank's first president, William A. Bird (1797-1878), upon his death in 1878. He was also a member of the board of directors for Buffalo & Erie Railroad, a company in which he was a large shareholder.
Harrison was a Whig and served on the Buffalo Common Council twice. In 1853 he was the Whig candidate for mayor, running against Democrat Eli Cook (1814-1865), who won in a close election. Harrison joined the Republican party after the Whig party collapsed in 1856. Although he did not continue to pursue a political career he remained a strong supporter of the Republicans. A long-time art lover and collector, Harrison was a life member of the Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, which was established as a public fine arts gallery in 1862. He was also a member of Trinity Episcopal Church, where he served as a vestryman. Harrison died unexpectedly on 21 November 1882. He had been ill, but was optimistic he would recover. He died instantly while getting up from bed.
James Cooke Harrison married Mary Wilson Pearce (8 July 1820-11 June 1891), daughter of George and Eliza Pearce. Although the parish register shows they married 16 July 1842, Mary insisted the correct date was 25 August 1842 and they celebrated their anniversary on that day. They had two children. Lilly was born around 1846, and died in August of 1848 after a long illness. Mary Pearce Harrison was born in Erie on 12 November 1849. She attended private schools in Buffalo and a select girls' school in New York City, Mrs. Ogden Hoffman's French and English Boarding and Day School, from 1864-1868.
Williams Family (Series IV)
William Williams was born in Bolton, Connecticut to Samuel (8 February 1785-5 July 1876) and Sarah White Williams (1787-22 August 1849) on 6 September 1815. He was one of nine children. He grew up in Bolton and attended local schools. At the age of 17 Williams moved to Georgia where he was involved in commercial business between New England, the West Indies and ports in the southern United States. He soon became ill and returned to Bolton. From there he went to work for one of his maternal uncles at a bank in Norwich, Connecticut and then moved to Windham, Connecticut where he clerked at another uncle's bank, Bank of Windham.
Williams met Lovisa Kirkland Stedman (11 September 1815-27 September 1895), while living in Windham. Lovisa Kirkland Stedman was the daughter of Griffin (27 September 1770-?) and Elizabeth Gordon (?-1822) Stedman, a wealthy and influential family in Hartford, Connecticut. They married 9 October 1838. The Williams had three children: Catherine Stedman (4 August 1839-17 January 1841), Griffin Stedman (11 September 1841-7 March 1911), and Charles Gordon (23 December 1847-6 September 1897).
After marrying Williams took a cashier job at Bank of Sandusky in Sandusky, Ohio. Deciding Sandusky did not offer the opportunities he desired, he and his wife settled in Buffalo in 1839. His uncle George C. White (28 November 1804-30 May 1869) made Williams a partner in his banking business, and they opened a branch in Buffalo called White and Williams. The bank prospered, and reorganized in 1844 as White's Bank of Buffalo. Williams continued to clerk there for 12 years. In 1856 Williams and some friends founded Clinton Bank of Buffalo. It survived the panic of 1857, but closed four years later as the financial markets faced continued uncertainty.
The late 1840's and early 1850's saw tremendous growth in railroads. Around 1851 a railroad was proposed from Buffalo to Erie and State Line Railroad Company was formed to construct it. Williams, by then a prominent financier, served as one of the original directors and later as president of the company. In the period after the Civil War he was actively engaged in promoting and financing the growth of the railroads. As president of Buffalo and Erie Railroad, Williams helped orchestrate its consolidation with other railroads to form Lake Shore and Michigan Southern Railroad Company in 1869. He was elected first vice president of the new corporation. He served as a director of Michigan Southern Railroad Company and in 1873 was elected a director of Buffalo, New York and Philadelphia Railroad Co., where he had considerable control of the railroad's business affairs. In addition to his involvement with the railroads, Williams financed a number of other industrial concerns such as mining and canals.
Williams also played a role in Buffalo's social and cultural affairs. He was one of the incorporators of the Buffalo Fine Arts Academy in 1862. He also helped establish the Buffalo Club, an exclusive men's club, which organized in 1867.
Williams started his political career in 1841, when he was elected City Treasurer of Buffalo. In 1845 he was elected to the city's Common Council. During the Civil War while loyal to the Union cause, he was opposed to President Abraham Lincoln (1809-1865). He gave money to help raise troops and was a member of the Union Continentals, a home guard of men age 45 and over organized by former president Millard Fillmore (1800-1874). In 1866 Williams was elected to the New York Assembly on the Democratic ticket; he was re-elected the following year.
In 1870 Williams accepted the 30th New York District Democratic nomination for the Forty-second Congress on the condition that Grover Cleveland (1837-1908), a young lawyer in his personal attorney's office, would be nominated for sheriff of Erie County. Williams helped finance both campaigns, and both men were elected. He served from 1871-1873, but was unsuccessful in his attempt to be re-elected to the Forty-third Congress in 1872.
Williams withdrew from politics and business as his health deteriorated in 1874. He suffered severe financial losses during the panic of 1873, which his family believed hastened his decline. He died at home 10 September 1876. Lovisa returned to Connecticut where she lived with their son, Charles. She died in Windsor, Connecticut 27 September 1895.
Charles Gordon Williams attended public and private schools in Buffalo, and later Cheshire Academy in Cheshire, Connecticut. After finishing school in 1868, his parents sent him on a year of travel in Europe. Upon his return he worked in the oil business in and around Bradford, Pennsylvania for several years. He married Georgiana Metcalfe (15 February 1852-20 July 1930), daughter of George H. (ca. 1827-?) and Matilda (ca. 1827-?) Metcalfe, on 20 January 1874 and they settled in Brookfield Centre, Connecticut, where they lived the rest of their lives.
Griffin Stedman Williams, called Sted by family and friends, attended schools in Buffalo and Ohio, and completed his education at Rev. Dr. Thomas C. Reed (ca. 1810-?)'s Walnut Hill School in Geneva, New York in 1859. His parents wanted Williams to go to Yale University, an institution to which both of their families had ties, but he decided to enter into business.
In 1859 he took a clerkship in Clinton Bank of Buffalo, and later went to work for James C. Harrison. His early business career was disrupted with the outbreak of the Civil War. He was eager to join the army although his parents objected strongly to the idea. Williams finally convinced his parents to let him join, and his father obtained a commission for him in 1862 as a first lieutenant in the 132nd New York Volunteers. He was assigned as aide-de-camp to Brigadier General Francis Barretto Spinola (1821-1891) and served around Suffolk, Virginia and Newbern, North Carolina. In 1863 Williams served with the Army of the Potomac, and then followed Spinola north. Williams contracted a severe case of camp fever while in the field that disabled him, and he received an honorable discharge 10 February 1864.
Williams returned to Buffalo to recuperate in his parents' home. His father arranged for a year of travel and Williams set sail in May 1864 for the British Isles, Europe, and Middle East. He spent another year travelling in 1869, sailing from San Francisco for Japan and Europe. His ship passed through the Suez Canal, which was in its first year of existence, and returned to the United States in 1870.
Williams grew up socializing with the family of James C. Harrison. He married Mary Pearce Harrison on 20 December 1871 in Buffalo. The Williams had three children: Harrison (28 February 1873-9 June 1946), Mary Stedman (5 February 1875- ?), and Gordon (1 September 1876-4 October 1925).
On 9 September 1885 Williams was appointed Consul of the United States at Nottingham, England by President Grover Cleveland, and he sailed for England in October. His family joined him in 1886, and Williams held the consulate post until 1890. The family spent that year in Europe before returning to Buffalo in 1891. Following his wife's death in 1909, Stedman Williams moved to New York City to be near his sons, Harrison and Gordon. He died 8 March 1911 after a long illness.
Mary Stedman Williams was educated in Buffalo and Europe. She attended St. Margaret's School in Buffalo, Bois de Fey School in Switzerland, and schools in England and France. On 1 October 1902 she married Frederick Bradlee Winslow (27 July 1873-1937), son of Walter Thatcher (1843-1909) and Sarah Louise Sears (ca. 1845-?) Winslow, in Buffalo. Walter Winslow was an architect and partner at Winslow & Wetherall, a noted and prolific Boston architectural firm. Frederick and Mary resided in Boston, where he was a prominent physician. Mary was known for her expertise in classical Greek.
Gordon Williams was educated in England, Europe, and Buffalo. While his father was posted in England from 1886-1890, Williams attended University School in Nottingham, and from 1890-1891 he attended Chateau de Lancy School near Geneva, Switzerland. He completed his education in local schools when the family returned to Buffalo in 1891.
Williams joined the 65th Infantry Regiment of the New York State National Guard, which was federalized in May of 1898 for service in the Spanish-American War. The regiment was sent in sections to Camp Alger near Falls Church, Virginia, arriving by 21 May. Williams caught typhoid fever in the camp and returned to his parents' home in Buffalo to recover.
He was employed briefly as a reporter for the Buffalo Express, and in 1900 went to work for American Telegraph & Telephone Co. He was transferred to the company's New York City general offices and later became a Wall Street broker. In 1914 he became the American representative for a British company with oil interests in Venezuela, where he lived during the winter of 1914-1915.
In February of 1917 he was asked by Anne Morgan (25 July 1873-29 January 1952) to go to France and carry out an independent study of the work of the American Fund for French Wounded prior to the United States' entry into World War I. The American Fund for French Wounded, established by Morgan, was the largest relief agency operating in Europe, providing hospital aid and ambulance services behind the Allied front. Williams returned to the United States in June and volunteered for officer's training camp. After graduating in December of 1917 he was commissioned a first lieutenant in the army.
He felt it was his duty to serve on the front lines and was anxious to be sent to Europe, but he met resistance from army officials because of his age. First assigned harbor duty in New Jersey, Williams was then sent to Camp Mills on Long Island, New York to assist with troop training. While at Camp Mills, Williams met up with an old friend, Brigadier-General Munroe McFarland (28 June 1867-1924), who was commander of the 162nd Infantry Brigade, 81st Division of the American Expeditionary Force. McFarland asked Williams to join him as his aide-de-camp, and they sailed for France 30 July 1918. Williams applied for a transfer to the front lines, and on 8 November 1918 he joined the 323rd Infantry in the trenches. He received a citation for his work rescuing troops stranded in an exposed position during operations November 9-11, 1918.